<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bualimmm.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://bualimmm.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-05T10:26:12+00:00</updated><id>https://bualimmm.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A personal website for Mahdi Buali. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Arabic Calligraphy and Poetry</title><link href="https://bualimmm.github.io/blog/2024/arabic-calligraphy-poetry/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arabic Calligraphy and Poetry"/><published>2024-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bualimmm.github.io/blog/2024/arabic-calligraphy-poetry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bualimmm.github.io/blog/2024/arabic-calligraphy-poetry/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/cal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/cal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/cal-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/cal.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Translation: A house is not made beautiful by its construction, but by its inhabitants. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="random"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Translation: A house is not made beautiful by its construction, but by its inhabitants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intelligence and Engineering</title><link href="https://bualimmm.github.io/blog/2024/intelligence-and-engineering/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intelligence and Engineering"/><published>2024-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bualimmm.github.io/blog/2024/intelligence-and-engineering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bualimmm.github.io/blog/2024/intelligence-and-engineering/"><![CDATA[<p>I just finished up a course on NeuroSymbolic AI, and there was this one question that kept popping up: What is intelligence, anyway? It seemed that field experts traditionally believed intelligence to be the human ability to use complex symbols, such as language, for communication.</p> <p>But the recent advances in Large Language Models (LLMs) debunked this hypothesis; LLMs demonstrate a remarkable ability to utilize symbols for communication, arguably even better than humans, through a purely statistical autoregressive process. This doesn’t really fit our general perception of intelligence, contributing to a new ambiguity about intelligence definition. I believe it is a similar ambiguity to when we try to explain what love is! In this essay, I want to share my current thoughts on what intelligence is, not love.</p> <p>Before I say exactly what I think intelligence is, I want to talk about the thing that always comes to mind when I think about it: complex systems. Whenever I travel and have nothing to do but overthink, I’m always amazed by the aviation ecosystem. It seems almost implausible that humans built these giant metal birds that fly through the air, following invisible paths at crazy speeds, and connect different continents with minimal risk. Then you land, and there is this whole other world of complex systems working together to make sure everyone gets their bags and the planes are ready to go again. Aviation, the global economy, even laptops – these are all examples of super complex systems that manifest human intelligence.</p> <p>One way to figure out what intelligence is to think about what it is not. This concept appears to highly correlate with oversimplification. It is simpler to believe in a single family controlling the world than to try to understand the global economy and politics. It is simpler to attribute vice to the Illuminati than to read about the history of morality. And it is simpler to think one AI model will solve all our problems than to learn statistics. Oversimplification appears to be inherent in human nature, as it provides easily digestible answers and justifies a reluctance to learn. However, intelligence seems to be the key to overcoming this natural tendency towards oversimplification, allowing us to truly grasp the dynamics of our complex world and arrive at meaningful conclusions.</p> <p>Given that complex systems are a manifestation of intelligence, and that intelligence itself is what enables us to navigate complexity, I’ve come to believe that intelligence is the ability to plan, build, and run a system of various components, while constantly refining its processes. Basically, intelligence is the ability to engineer stuff. This probably explains why I recently keep saying “we should engineer it” whenever I’m talking about problems!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[documentation of my current thoughts about intelligence]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Great Tips by Great People</title><link href="https://bualimmm.github.io/blog/2024/tips/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Great Tips by Great People"/><published>2024-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bualimmm.github.io/blog/2024/tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bualimmm.github.io/blog/2024/tips/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m trying to keep track of the career tips I learn from the great people I’m fortunate to meet:</p> <ul> <li> <p>“Everyone’s gotta sell something, whether it’s an idea or a product. If you can’t get people on board with your solution, it doesn’t matter how good it actually is.”</p> </li> <li> <p>“In our field, it’s normal to sometimes feel alone or overwhelmed. But on our team, let’s make sure no one feels both at the same time.”</p> </li> <li> <p>When you’re dealing with the big picture and someone deep in the weeds asks you a detailed question because they’re feeling swamped, try saying “you tell me.” It might sound weird, but it can work wonders. Chances are, they know more about the problem than anyone, and they just need a little encouragement to figure it out.</p> </li> <li> <p>“Sometimes, to truly understand the root causes of a problem and why people struggle to solve it, all we need is empathy for those facing it.”</p> </li> <li> <p>“When you’re speaking, try to structure your thoughts so that your audience always has a sense of where you’re going next.”</p> </li> <li> <p>“When someone insists on making a mistake, don’t try to stop them by force. Just let them know you think it’s a mistake, and if it turns out you’re right, they’ll likely come back to you for help.”</p> </li> <li> <p>Kick off every meeting by going over the agenda, and wrap it up with a quick recap of the actionable items.</p> </li> <li> <p>“Don’t get married to your ideas. There are always better ones out there.”</p> </li> <li> <p>“You’re stupid if you blindly do a task just because someone asked. Always understand the “why” behind what you’re doing.”</p> </li> <li> <p>Before you suggest anything to someone, take a moment to ask about their interests.</p> </li> <li> <p>“Relax and enjoy the moment, because time keeps on ticking regardless.”</p> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="random"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m trying to keep track of the career tips I learn from the great people I’m fortunate to meet:]]></summary></entry></feed>